So far we have been looking at bandit algorithms
right or the immediate reinforcement learning
and so what we are going to start from today
is looking at the full reinforcement ionic
problem right.
.
So we know earlier already about the full
RL problem right so what are the complications
that we are going to insert here States we
already looked at states in contextual mandates
right temporal dependents right the sequential
nature of the problem is something that we
are going to introduce here so what we are
going to look at is that we will assume that
there is a there is an environment okay and
the agent interacts with the environment at
any point the agent senses the state the environment
is in okay.
Then in response to that the agent takes a
action which is then applied to the environment
okay so the agent sensors the state the environment
is in SST right and it takes an action that
gets applied to the environment and as a result
of applying this action environment changes
to a state St + 1 which then gets fed back
into the agent has the current state St and
then you keep doing this in a loop right so
this could go on indefinitely then all there
could be a well designated stopping state
right if you reach the state you stop the
trends okay a group of states I mean you can
always this is the strict right.
So when I say that is a starting state and
the stopping state it could very well be a
group of starting states and the group of
stopping states I can always define a dummy
state to which all the states go to right
so I can always say that is a single starting
state in a single stopping state right so
that if a reach of exposition so I will keep
saying that makes sense and even if there
are multiple states where you will stop I
can insert one dummy state and say that automatically
as soon as you reach one of these states you
will make a transition to the dummy state
and you will stop them okay.
So they will always be a one-stop state one
starts taking right so that might happen and
apart from this
you also get a remote signal from the environment
okay this is like as mentioning earlier this
is a convenience a modeling convenience that
we put the reward in the environment okay
that is because we want to put the reward
in a place which is outside the agents direct
control right agent should not this arbitrarily
say okay I okay I am getting a reward of five
now right.
So it should get this reward as a result of
the behavior in the world okay it cannot just
arbitrarily set its own rewards okay so that
is the reason we put the reward in the environment
okay so that is outside in reality right this
will be a very much more complex picture right
because if you think about it I mean I have
been repeatedly saying that all biological
agents of reinforcement learning agents right
humans are reinforcement learning agents so
do you have a separate reward conduit right.
We have a reward sensing mechanism somewhere
right so you only have what you sense from
the world right so you look around you see
whatever is whatever inputs that are coming
in whether you are in you could being interesting
food you could be looking at the outside world
right somebody might be touching you on the
skin whatever ray so you are taking in all
these complex sensory inputs and other kinds
of actual physical ingestible inputs okay
and then you are converting them into rewards
right so that is how the rewards happen right.
So if you are hungry and you eat okay that
is that is rewarding right but then you and
find out that you have I do not know eaten
something that is gone stale right let us
not rewarding it is in fact opposite of it
right and if you have not hungry and somebody
just gives you something to eat you just eat
for the sake of you know I give me company
and then you go and eat some really bad food
and things like that so there is no immediately
water part from the company part of it but
the act of eating itself does not give you
any immediate reward but probably we have
a consequence in the long run Yeah right so
go eat some right foot just because your friend
asked you to eat will have consequences in
the in the long run right .
So rewards are if he thinks right I mean so
we are going to make it very concrete right
I am going to say that is this some mechanism
in the environment that gives you a reward
but if you really think about it these rewards
are or everywhere right in fact the last few
years so Andy Balto was asked going around
asking this question where do robots come
from right so when was he here 2009 yeah so
I hosted him here in 2009 and one of the talks
I mean at that time the talk he was going
around giving everywhere was flagged or watts
come from okay so it was it is really an unforgettable
thing yeah.
So also this is not very clear so take it
with a pinch of salt when I say that the environment
is going to give you a reward signal like
the robots could come from anywhere right
in fact it is not even clear what is the agent
what is the environment so you have a lot
of Robotics guys here right suppose I am having
a robot learning problem right so what would
be the agent what would be the environment
the robot is agent really okay let us say
I give you a navigation problem or a reaching
problem let us say I am trying to train a
robot to reach out and pick an object on the
table.
In the environment is the workspace where
were they armed no but what about the angle
of the arm we sit in the environment or is
it part of the agent so let us see where is
agent then so the arm is not part of the agent
the one controlling the arm is the Agent so
it becomes tricky various we are actually
think about it is not like okay as a robot
the robot is a agent everything outside the
robot is environment right so it is not that
boundaries are not drawn as neatly around
the physical entities right suppose let us
consider forget about robots let us say you
are driving a car okay so who is the agent
what is the agent and what is the environment
there.
Right I mean always the right answer is depends
right but what does it depend on right in
this case the agent could be the car wait
the environment could be the road right so
as a human being sitting and driving a car
you can look at okay what is the velocity
which the car is moving okay and what is the
direction which the car is moving about pedestrians
jumping in front of me right and all those
things right so this could be your and it
just could be your environment right and the
agent itself is the car you know I am controlling
the car on the other hand the environment
could include the car right and the agent
could be the human sitting there and you can
think of okay.
How much how much am I pushing my foot down
on the pedal which petals should I be keeping
my feet on first case right and then should
I how much how about what talk should I apply
to the steering wheel right where should I
be turning my head to look at right would
I be looking at the mirror should I look at
front right or should I be looking down at
my phone right so all of these things decisions
that you have to make right while you are
driving right so there is this interface now
the agent environment interface becomes a
human when the car right or it could be even
more right he can go further back it can even
go further back into the human right thinking
about okay which okay I am talking about the
motor cortex right.
So which neurons in my motor cortex should
for now so that my arm switches enough so
that I turn the wheel this much right so which
neurons should fire in my motor I mean the
autonomous nervous system so that my leg actually
pushes down with some kind of pressure right
so I could I could think of depending on the
kind of problem that I am solving and I could
think of drawing this agent environment boundary
anywhere right and then not arbitrarily anywhere
but you can think of multiple places where
the same set of interacting entities are there
right but you have very different kinds of
modeling that you could do.
Like it is not very clear when I say there
is an agent there is an environment do not
expect people to come and give you okay this
is the agent here is environment now come
up with a reinforcement learning algorithm
that will solve this problem right so typically
you will have to think about this figure out
what is a right abstraction that you would
need right before you go so I start a solution
for this right so this is something which
you have to keep in mind nobody is giving
this to you a priori right so having said
all of this or one other way of thinking about
how this interaction proceeds right.
So model all the caveats I have been giving
to you there is an agent okay it senses the
state of the environment it takes an action
okay and then that causes a change in the
state of the environment right so having said
all of this you can think of the interactions
as proceeding like this so I have St right
I sense that I take action 80 okay that causes
new state St + 1 under reward so this is a
slight quark of the book itself right where
the reward corresponding to the state and
action at time T is labeled as RT + 1 okay
so this is a quirk in the book and the reason
they say is typically the next state and the
next reward or determined at the same time.
And therefore it is a makes more sense to
label both of them with T +1 okay so one thing
here in the Bandit case I was making a distinction
between N and D okay I am going back to using
T here but the T could be discrete time as
well in fact for most of the course RT is
going to be discreet okay in fact T did not
even be
time T did not even be time okay so T is steps
so what are you talking about here typically
these are my decision apex right when I say
T = 1 that means I am taking my first decision
you say T equal to 2 that means I am taking
my second decision right this is typically
okay.
Sometimes I am also interested in cases where
I do not take any decisions but the state
keeps changing over time but for most parts
when I say when advanced / 1 that is typically
at the point where I'm required to take the
next decision okay so later we will actually
look at a still a discrete-time case but where
decisions need not happen at every time tick
so we look at that case as well later but
not immediately okay so most part of it assume
that T is a decision tick ok not a time tick
when T goes from T to T +1 that means have
taken other decisions the decisions could
not need not necessarily take the same time.
For example consider the game of chess right
so each move that you make I mean so initially
you will be making moves very rapidly right
because you are playing from a standard opening
play or something and later on you actually
have to study their board position and then
you have to think about it and make moves
right but I still count each everything as
a single move right so you do not say the
first few moves were all count as one fourth
of a movie each or anything because you did
it very fast so just exactly like that so
each move itself could take different amounts
of time right.
I am not worried about it and the intervals
at which you are asked to make decisions might
also be non-uniform I am not worried about
it okay this is the basic setting I am having
later when we talk about hierarchical RL will
start worrying about the duration of decisions
if I take one action now how long will it
take for that action to complete and those
kinds of things we worry about later right
now we are assuming that every action takes
the same time to complete so time with encodes
here okay.
So that is basically hit this case keeps going
let us oh will denote by S + that distinguished
terminal state right so this just keeps going
until I S+ or it just keeps going in definitely
if I there is no distinguished terminal strength
okay any questions of a setup is clear right
so what we are going to do okay next thing
I want to talk about is
the reward itself so I am going to be very
religiously following chapter 3 in the book
right and I did ask people to read ahead to
Chapter three how many of you actually read
chapter three, four my god you did you put
your hand up.
Okay then not content so 4 people yeah sorry
you are busy doing the assignments is it he
will release the assignment from chapter 3
as well so from now onwards what we will do
is before I start the chapter will release
the assignments will it help letting the same
of course not the programming assignment yes
so when is when is the second return assignment
due Friday is it so if you release some questions
today they will be able to finish it before
Friday night I only promise I will not release
it on Thursday.
Then I promise I will not release questions
on Thursday right I did not say anything ever
Wednesday a world is not giving any opinion
you were just thinking about okay they have
not do anything to him this I am the one who
will get beaten up okay so it will extend
the deadline to Monday and then give them
additional assignments today yes so the people
who read the head so what does the chapter
say about reward functions this is anything
but word shear anything else about the robot
so classically reinforcement learning assumes
that the reward is a scalar quantity alright
so the rewards are so the words are scalar
and it is outside the direct control of agent.
That is why I told you we put it in the environment
yeah we will come to that right so what does
it mean that agent cannot arbitrarily set
the reward it has to do it through the interaction
with the environment okay so that is essentially
the two main things that we need so the more
important thing here is the assumption that
the rewards are scalar right so what does
it mean it means is just a number so it might
look that it is a pretty weak model for the
rewards but if you remember we talked about
a wide variety of applications of reinforcement
learning in the first lecture and then all
of those applications that we went through
we were actually looking at scalar robots.
Right so it does turn out that variety of
settings where you can use the scale or what
and get away with it right but there are in
cases where you might have to make some kind
of calls about trade-offs between how much
importance you want to give to one event versus
another so for example let us again take the
reaching tasks that we had right so the so
when I want to reach out to an already set
the rewards here once a graph it I will give
a reward right I can give you some more like
can give you a reward of 10 or something when
I graph the yeah but then I need to optima
need to get there right.
So I what I am trying to do is optimize my
reward function if you remember the whole
problem in the reinforcement learning is too
well I see something if you mentioned in the
very beginning the problem in RL is to behave
in such a way so that you get as much as reward
as possible in the long run right so if I
do not give you any reward function I will
just be flailing around right I could be happily
moving waving my hand around not doing anything
in regard to grasping the object right.
So I need to give some kind of a reward either
for grasping the object or how else would
you do this negative reward for every time
step I keep flailing around right it is like
you are in constant pain right and the pain
will stop once you hold this right because
the episode ends and you stop getting minus
once then right so like somebody keeps poking
you with a pine all the time keep go and you
reach this is how we try yeah anyway any of
any animal that draws a vehicle right you
keep pushing it in the side until it actually
reaches the destination right.
I mean and then humans are very cruel man
I mean anyway so that is how we do it right
so but then instead also set sufficient so
you do not really want to strain your hand
right so I mean there are joint limits right
so you really do not want to come up with
a crisp grasp that looks like this right this
also valid I have got the phone right so you
do not want to do that I want to give some
kind of you know additional pain right if
I do things like this right so if in fact
for me it actually was painful right but so
you want to do this communicate this to the
boat that is how much additional pain do you
give it.
So grabbing this thing let us say gives you
a reward of 10 right and doing that gives
you a reward of say-100 so what is going to
happen they are going to be very cautious
right in trying to grab it right but if grabbing
this gives you the word of 100 right I am
doing that gives you a reward of -0.1 you
would still be cautious because I am being
optimal right so 99.1 miss was than 99.5 so
I will still be cautious about avoiding those
but I will not go to two significant extent
to do that because I am still getting my -1’s
right so the longer I take to get to the gate
to a grasp right the more -1 I am going to
get right and the better form the grass place
the fewer -1’s I am going to get.
So there is some trade-offs I will form at
some point right but where the trade-off quite
lies depends on the magnitude of the reverse
I am going to give you as well so if I am
going to give you a -1000 for doing something
like this right then I will be more careful
right so these are all trade-offs right when
you design the problem but so how do you set
this reward functions well understood problems
like grasping or reaching or robotics in general
right you can look at the problem that you
are trying to solve and try to figure out
okay which are undesirable configurations
okay,
So very expensive robot so I do not want to
break it so let me make sure that all these
other things have a highly high negative values
right Andorra versus a cheap robot or what
I really want to do is get there as soon as
I can okay do not mind throwing 300 robot
set it because each robot costs only 1rs right
then I can just not worry about crashing and
burning a few along the way right so it depends
on the domain right so there is still a significant
trade off that I will have to think about
right so even though I am saying it is a scalar
quantity there are instances where I will
have to kind of put multiple outcomes right
multiple outcomes on the same scale it makes
it a little tricky just like in this case
I mean that is an outcome associated with
success which is grasping it and that is outcome
associated with well not really failures but
outcomes associated with undesirable events
along the way.
So I have to put all of these on the same
scale and I have to do it might have been
more convenient if you could have thought
of okay 104 that k- 5 for this but these are
just things that you need to avoid know if
there is some other way I can communicate
these things to robot then that might be a
better mechanism it turns out it is hard to
come up with the appropriate optimization
set up for doing this so the scalar robot
thing A is pretty powerful and B kind of gels
in some sense with how we also do decision-making
at the end of the day you are very good at
judging trade-offs right.
So whenever as soon as you start thinking
of doing these kinds of trade-offs in some
sense you are putting these on the same scale
right the putting them on the same scale because
they only then you can think about trade-offs
so in that way also it seems to be natural
and the third thing is having a single scalar
value makes it easier for us to optimize the
solution right we can always get a good optimal
solution this is for various reasons so scalar
values are fine and so I think that is one
of the homework questions which ask you to
think about scalar values a little bit more
I mean think and reason about it.
And so what else do we need the reward to
do well mathematically we need the rewards
to be bounded we are talking about biological
systems is not really a criterion and because
I mean it has to be physical right so you
cannot have an unbounded neural spike in your
brain for corresponding to a robot right so
you may just fry your brain right so but when
talking about mathematical a certain settings
you really want through what to be bounded
right so basically that is it so one other
thing later on we would like the robot to
be frequent I will explain this later like
once we start looking at learning algorithms
and system but this essentially means that
it should not be that I get rewards say once
in a million time steps.
There is very little very limited literature
in this right so the one alternative which
people have explored is to look at vector-valued
rewards where each component of the reward
corresponds to a different thing that you
want to achieve and these are called typically
multi-criteria RL right there are very few
papers or maybe five or six papers out there
which talk about multi criteria reinforcement
learning in fact there is a corresponding
optimization thing also called multi-criteria
optimization right.
So where people talk about different notions
of optimality event so what exactly is optimal
rate so optimal is where the objective function
you reach a minimum of objective function
but now if you went look at it in multiple
dimensions so you may end up reaching some
kind of saddle points also right so what exactly
is the Optima in this case so people talk
about those kinds of characterization.
So there is more work in multi-agent settings
in looking at more richer reward functions
than in single agent RL right yeah very little
out there and it will be interesting to come
up with some kind of qualitative feedback
as well instead of looking at this kind of
a quantitative feedback and if you like that
kind of work there are there is some kind
of work in fuzzy RL where the feedback signal
is a fussy signal not much again very little
and one more things I want to mention but
all of those are scalar I mean there are all
kinds of work on like instead of looking at
the reward but look at the perception of reward
and so on so forth.
But all of these are still scalar quantities
and they are not vector valued quantities
but it is a much h richer notion of feedback
then what you what is typically a reward functions
so what we mean by frequently said you should
not be getting rewards like once in a million
time steps or something then you will never
learn anything right you are trying to optimize
rewards and regardless of what you do for
a million time steps you get nothing is too
long a horizon for you to learn anything over
right so typically you expect more reward
to come to you along the way okay.
So that is what robot so policy so what is
it so I am just talking about different components
of a reinforcement learning system okay so
we talked about states and actions right basically
the agent and the environment now you're talking
about the robot okay the next thing you want
to talk about is the policy so what is the
policy no 0 is non infirmity of right I really
cannot change my unless I have gotten a -1
so where I do not know if zero is good or
bad I mean I really cannot change anything
based on 0 but that is a good point yeah.
So when we say frequent rewards I do mean
frequent non zero rewards
right so we know what the policy is right
all of us know what policies are so what is
the policy
so I am going to denote a policy as this as
a conditional thing from now on so what is
this is essentially the probability that there
is a probability that at time T the agent
will take action eighth given that at time
T the state is s.
So ideally I should have a T there right so
p T(A, S) is a probability that at time T
I will take action A given that at time T
the state was S okay so normally for most
of the material that we cover right I will
be looking at what are known as stationary
policies so what is the stationary policy
the stationary policy is something which is
essentially so regardless of the value of
T I will be using the same probability so
the probability that let us say my state is
1 right probability that when give me some
other symbol to use a state let us say my
status l okay I do not think I used L for
anything so far have a we have in the proofs
you use L or is it yeah let us say okay fine
let us use it one then people can all of you
are smart enough to figure out this right.
So let us say state is 1 right so I do not
care whether it is one that time one whether
s1 is equal to 1 or S 25 is equal to 1 the
probability that I will take action A1 will
be the same right the probability I will take
action A2 will be the same so essentially
what I am saying is.
.
Probability that A1 equal to a1 give S1 = 1
= probability that something like this okay
right so this is what I mean by stationary
that is what I am saying here so if I want
to explicitly talk about non-stationary policies
okay I will use the p T notation okay if I
am talking about stationary policies I will
just use the p notation.
Okay so what is my policy the what is a goal
in trying to come up with a policy see one
even go there it I am just defining things
right a non-stationary policy is just a collection
of functions collection of probability distributions
one for each time step at a stationary policy
is a single well it is actually also a set
of probability distributions one for each
state right a non stationary policy is a collection
of such sets one for each time step as well
as one for each state that is basically it
how you derive how we derive anon-stationary
policy or how we learn it from data and other
things they are independent questions I am
just talking about it is simple definition
of the quantity when you learn your goal should
be a stationary policy right the end goal
can be a stationary policy where you have
a stationary there is no subsequent we will
come to that right so there are different
time scales at which you can learn right.
So I can have a stationary policy run the
full episode using the stationary policy and
then take the rewards I get and then use that
update my parameters and come up with a new
stationary policy right so these times I am
talking about the T here is essentially the
index over a single interaction okay I am
not talking about multiple interactions over
the single interaction right suppose I start
from some s0 I come and end at s+ over that
interaction my policy stays fixed that seems
to be a reasonable assumption right.
So you could think of having states learning
a sequence of stationary policies so what
is my goal in learning a policy here is to
learn something that will maximize the reward
that I get right but not individually but
something that will maximize it in the longer
okay so what do I mean by that suppose I am
riding a cycle right so suppose you leave
your hands and say they look at me or something
like that might give you a temporary kick
you know I feel really good about myself but
then you met the next minute you might ram
into another vehicle or a tree or a building
whatever right and get injured right.
So that is something that gives you a depends
but hopefully there is something that will
deter you from doing crazy things on a cycle
the next time around right so the short-term
reward was just feeling good about you for
one minute and the long term penalty was getting
into a cast or whatever right so these kinds
of things are odd or even simple things like
in chess you know the first thing kids they
try to capture the Queen and whole bunch of
other things and then as a result end up losing
the game right so this can something so you
do not look for short-term rewards you should
look for something that maximizes your rewards
in the long term.